montgomerycountymd.gov 2003-04-19

# Welcome to the Montgomery County Maryland Website

Thank you for using the Montgomery County, Maryland Government (hereafter, the County) web portal. We hope that you find our web portal to be a convenient and valuable resource for interacting with County Governmental organizations. In order to be of value, we know that you must be able to trust that any information you provide while interacting with the County will be kept private and secure. This document represents our Privacy Policy and it is intended to serve two purposes:

  * To provide guidance to County employees regarding how to develop, secure and maintain the County portal and
  * To assure you that your information will be kept private and secure.  
It is our statement concerning how your information will be protected. If you have questions or doubts concerning the privacy of your information, you should consult this document. If, after consulting this document you still have questions or doubts, you should contact:

Montgomery County, Maryland Government   
ATTN: Renee Yue  
51 Monroe Street  
Suite 100  
Rockville, Maryland 20850 

The County adheres to and follows the practices and procedures described below for the purpose of assuring the privacy of visitors to the County web portal. These practices and procedures are approved by the Department of Technology Services, the Office of the County Attorney, and the Office of the County Executive. The County reserves the right to change these practices and procedures at any time without prior notice. The following is not intended and should not be interpreted as a contract of any nature, either stated or implied. 

In addition to the above, the County also complies with the requirements for administering information systems as established in the Maryland Public Information Act (PIA) Title 10, Subtitle 6, Part III of the State Government Article. The PIA covers all counties, including Montgomery County, cities, towns, school districts, and special districts like soil conservation or sanitary sewage districts.   
Beginning October 1, 2000 the PIA restricts the County's ability to create "personal records" and collect "personal information" The County cannot create personal records unless it clearly establishes the need for that information. A "personal record" is one that names or, with reasonable certainty, otherwise identifies an individual by an identifying factor such as an address, a description, a finger or voice print, a number or a picture. The County establishes its need to create personal records by showing that it is either needed to execute some legal obligation like collect property taxes or that it is needed for administrative convenience. The County collects personal information directly from individuals who choose to use one or more of the County's web applications. Collecting personal information is necessary in order to deliver the services requested.

**CUSTOMER TRUST:**  
Fostering and maintaining the public's trust is a cornerstone of the County's web portal program. We appreciate the trust and confidence that you place in us by providing requested personal information  

**TRUSTe Privacy Program Registration Pending.**

To ensure your trust, the County is a pending licensee member of the TRUSTe Privacy Program. The TRUSTe Privacy Program is like a "Seal of Good Housekeeping." Licensees undergo a thorough privacy and security evaluation by the TRUSTe organization. Only when the licensee has successfully passed the evaluation can it display the TRUSTe trust-mark. The County is currently undergoing such an evaluation. Once the County passes the evaluation, it will display the TRUSTe trust-mark on its web portal. The trust-mark will link to this privacy statement. On our privacy statement there will be a "click to verify" seal which links, via secure server, to a TRUSTe validation page where the evaluated copy of our Privacy Policy will be available for review and comparison.   
As part of the TRUSTe evaluation, the County has disclosed procedures for the operation of the County web portal ([www.montgomerycountymd.gov](http://www.montgomerycountymd.gov/)). When you visit our web site displaying the TRUSTe trust-mark, you can expect to be informed of the following:

  * What organization in the County is collecting your information
  * What personally identifiable information of yours is collected
  * How your information is used
  * Whether and when the County uses Cookies
  * With whom your information may be shared
  * What choices are available to you regarding collection, use, and distribution of your information
  * What kind of security procedures are in place to protect you
  * How you can correct any inaccuracies in your information
  * Procedures for limiting employee access to information and 
  * How to contact the County

  * What organization(s) in the County is/are collecting the your information:

The County consists of those organizations and agencies identified in the County Organization Chart found on the web site. Only County organization(s) are permitted to collect information from you when you visit the County web site. These organizations most often collect information by asking you to fill out forms. The data you enter into the forms is stored in data bases. By completing forms you are electing to authorize the use of information that you provide. If you do not wish the County to use your information, you should not complete web forms. However, by electing not to complete web forms you, will be unable to receive the web services that you otherwise would have received.  

  * What personally identifiable information of yours is collected:

We endeavor to collect only the minimum amount of information needed. Though personal information may be required either by law or in order for us to provide a requested service, in doing so we try to minimize the scope of our information requests. Examples of personally identifiable information that we request can include your name, your address, your telephone number and e-mail address, and your bank account number and bank routing number and your credit card account number and credit card expiration date. The type of information we collect depends upon the application used and the products or services being requested. For each visitor, we also collect information about the Internet Protocol (IP) address, type of browser used, the date and time of the visit, and the IP addresses of the locations to which the visitor linked during his or her visit to our web site. This information is strictly used for statistical reporting purposes.  

  * How your information is used:

We collect, retain and use personal information only where we believe it is essential (and allowed by law) to perform our mission of providing products, services, information and other opportunities requested by our web portal visitors. Customer information collected, used, and retained at the County's web site is considered confidential and will not be shared for marketing or other unauthorized purposes.   

  * Whether and when the County uses cookies:

In certain web portal applications user information is collected and stored as "cookies." Cookies are then sent back and stored on the user's computer. Cookies allow computer applications to recognize you when you return after having logged off. This permits the application to start where you left off rather than require you to begin again from the beginning. Any County application or web page that uses cookies will identify itself as such. This information is handled in the same way as other user information obtained by the County. No user information is gathered through cookies except for that needed to run the specific application. To avoid the collection of information for cookies you should not use any applications that use cookies.   

  * With whom your information may be shared: (Restrictions on the disclosure of customer information)

The County does not sell, rent, or otherwise allow access to visitors/subscribers' information to/by any outside company or organization. We do not reveal specific information about subscribers or other personally identifiable data to unaffiliated third parties for their independent use, except if required to do so by law.   

  * What choices are available to you regarding collection, use, and distribution of your information:

The County web portal makes frequent use of web forms to collect information. As indicated above, you have the choice not to complete web forms. However, by electing not to complete web forms, you will be unable to receive the web services that you otherwise could/would have received.  
Some County web portal applications limit access to a selected group of people or organizations. The main method used to control access is the assignment of user names/identification numbers and the creation of passwords. Each potential program customer is given the option to obtain or create a user name/identification number and password. The username and password are needed to authenticate to and use the County web site application. The user name and password serve to prove your identity to the County thereby enabling you to use the application in order to obtain the products and/or services the application provides. You have the option of obtaining a user name/identification number and password or not. Not obtaining the required authentication capability is the same as not completing a web form - you prevent the collection of your information. However, you also forfeit the use of the application and the products or services it otherwise could/would deliver. You must obtain those products or services by some means other than through the web portal.   
Users electing to use the forms or applications are responsible to ensure all of their information is correct and that their user name/identification number and password are protected from unauthorized use.   

  * What kind of security procedures are in place to protect you: (Protection of information via established security procedures)

We are dedicated to the proposition that you have a right to privacy and data security on the web. The County sets and meets high security standards and follows rigorous procedures to prevent unauthorized access to or disclosure of customer information and to prevent unauthorized removal or alteration of data. We are committed to handling the information you provide responsibly.   
The County provides its users with a secure online experience by using a variety of security measures to maintain the safety of your personal information. All user registration information is contained behind a "firewall" and is only accessible by a limited number of employees who have special access rights to production systems. Password and credit card numbers are encrypted in a secure database located behind the "firewall". All sensitive/credit information supplied by users is transmitted via Secure Socket Layer (SSL) encryption technology and encrypted in the database. The County uses digital signature technology to assure you are interacting with the County and not an illegitimate replacement or substitute.   

  * How you can correct any inaccuracies in your information: (Maintenance of accurate information)

The County has established procedures to ensure that information is as accurate and current as is practical to enable us to conduct business with you. Although we strive to do things right the first time, we also respond to requests to correct inaccurate information in a timely manner. The user must contact the County immediately if they believe their information, including user names/identification numbers and passwords, has been corrupted, misused, or is incorrect.  

  * Procedures for limiting employee access to information:

Our network manager is instructed to limit employee access to personally identifiable information to only those employees who need access in order to perform their assigned duties. The network manager is instructed to enforce with his/her staff their responsibilities in protecting subscriber's information.   

  * How to contact the County:

We welcome your comments and invite you to contact us if you have any questions or concerns regarding this Privacy Policy. Contact us at: 

Montgomery County, Maryland   
ATTN: Renee Yue  
51 Monroe Street  
Suite 100  
Rockville, Maryland 20850   
or  

CUSTOMER SATISFACTION:   
Questions regarding this statement should be directed to the County by sending an e-mail [Customer.Service@co.mo.md.us](mailto:Customer.Service@co.mo.md.us). If you do not receive a response to your inquiry within five business days, please contact the County at [renee.yue@co.mo.md.us](mailto:ivan.galic@co.mo.md.us). If your inquiry has not been satisfactorily addressed, please contact TRUSTe at http://www.truste.org/users/users_watchdog.html. 

* * *

< top >

"Personal information" means information that identifies an individual including an individual's address, driver's license number, or any other identification number, medical or disability information, name, photograph or computer generated image, Social Security number, or telephone number. "Personal information" does not include an individual's driver's status, driving offenses, 5 digit zip code, or information on vehicular accidents.
